Hassel Smith papers
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Hassel Smith papers
circa 1900-2004, bulk 1930-1995
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Smith, Hassel
4.0 linear feet
The papers of California Bay-area painter and instructor Hassel Smith measure 4 linear feet and date from circa 1900-2004, bulk 1930-1995. Found within the papers are biographical materials, including a transcript of an interview conducted by Jan Butterfield in the 1980s, correspondence, personal business files, teaching files, writings by Smith and others, sketches, printed materials, and photographs of Smith, his family, friends, and artwork. There are audio recordings of a lecture series organized by Smith and of reviews of Smith's work. Correspondents include Paule Anglim, Elmer Bischoff, Andre Emmerich, Clyfford Still, Wayne Thiebaud, and many others.
Provenance
Hassel Smith donated most of his papers in several increments between 1980 and 1998. His son Joseph donated audio recordings in 1980, and Hassel Smith's widow Donna donated additional materials in 2004.
Related Material
Also found in the Archives of American Art is an oral history interview with Hassel Smith conducted by Paul Karlstrom, September 5, 1978.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Hassel Smith (1915-2007) was a California Bay area abstract expressionist painter, painting instructor at the California School of Fine Arts, and a lecturer at the University of California. His students included Roy De Forest, Sonia Gechtoff, and Frank Lobdell. Smith was also associated with the famed Los Angeles Ferus Gallery.
Hassel Smith was born on April 27, 1915, in Sturgis, Michigan, settling later with his family in San Mateo, California. He attended Northwestern University with the intention of becoming a chemist, but switched his majors to english and art history and graduated in 1936. Returning to California, Smith enrolled at the California School of Fine Arts (CSFA), and studied with the painter Maurice Sterne.
In 1937, he left school, and shared housing with his adopted brother Lewis in the Haight-Ashbury district and maintained a studio on Steiner Street. At the same time he worked as a social worker with men on "skid row" in San Francisco for the California Relief State Administration. Declared 4F by the draft board, Smith served various government agencies during World War II, including the Farm Security Administration and the U.S. Forest Service. During this period, he met and married June Meyers. He later described his government service and social work as having a strong influence on his art and politics.
In 1941, the University of California, Berkeley awarded Smith with the Abraham Rosenberg Fellowship, which allowed him to travel and paint outdoors at Angel's Camp in the Mother Lode of the Sierra foothills, along with Richard Hackett.
At the end of the war, Smith began teaching at the CSFA, joining faculty members Richard Diebenkorn, David Park, and Clyfford Still. Smith taught there until 1952. His students included Roy De Forest, Sonia Gechtoff, and Frank Lobdell. Smith continued to paint and exhibit work throughout the 1950s, and in 1958 became affiliated with the Ferus Gallery founded by Walter Hopps and Ed Kienholz. His wife June passed away in 1958. One year later, Smith remarried Donna Rafferty Harrington, and they had their son Bruce in 1960.
After an exhibition at the New Arts Gallery in Houston, London-based dealer Charles Gimpel invited Smith to exhibit his work in England. As a result of this, Smith moved to England in 1962, and spent a year living in Mousehole, a fishing village in Cornwall. He moved back to California and between 1963 to 1966 was a visiting lecturer at the University of California, Berkeley and the University of California, Los Angeles. In 1966, Smith accepted a position as Senior Lecturer at the West England College of Art in Bristol, England where he stayed until 1978. He finished his teaching career as a Principal Lecturer at the Cardiff College of Arts in Wales from 1978-1979.
Smith spent most of the next two decades painting and exhibiting, which included exhibitions at the Oakland Museum and the San José Museum of Art. In 1991, he was awarded an honorary doctorate by the San Francisco Art Institute (formerly the California School of Fine Arts). Due to failing health, Smith was forced to stop painting in 1997. Smith died in 2007 in Warminster, England, at the age of 91.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Southern California painter and instructor Hassel Smith measure 4 linear feet and date from circa 1900-2004, bulk 1930-1995. Found within the papers are correspondence, a transcript of an interview conducted by Jan Butterfield in the 1980s, personal business files, teaching files, writings by Smith and others, sketches, printed materials, and photographs of Smith, his family, friends, and Smith's artwork. There are audio recordings of a lecture series organized by Smith and of reviews of Smith's work. Correspondents include Paule Anglim, Elmer Bischoff, Andre Emmerich, Clyfford Still, Wayne Thiebaud, and many others.
Biographical materials include biographical sketches, curriculum vitae, genealogical materials, ephemera, and personal appointment books from the mid to late 1970s. Also found here is a transcript of an in-depth interview of Smith conducted by Jan Butterfield in the 1980s.
There is personal and professional correspondence with Paule Anglim, Elmer Bischoff, Andre Emmerich, Charles Gimpel of Gimpel Fils, Clyfford and Patricia Still, Kathryn Swanson of the New Arts Gallery, Wayne Thiebaud, family members, and many others.
Personal business records include art sales records, exhibition checklists, conservation and condition reports, and personal finance records. Teaching materials include class schedules, student lists, and syllabi. Also found are notes on topics such as American art and literature, artistic traits and forms, illusion, and women artists.
Writings by Smith include artist statements, creative writings, his thoughts on the art market and art institutions, the San Francisco art community, and social criticism. Writings by others consist primarily of essays about Smith and his work. There are also writings by Smith's friend Robert Wollard. Artwork includes sketches, doodles, and Christmas cards done by Smith, and a handful of artwork by others.
Printed materials include clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, and posters. Also found here are printed materials about other artists, schools where Smith enrolled or taught, Smith's general interests, and collages and flyers by Robert Wollard. There is a printed copy of the pictorial edition of the Communist Manifesto edited by Smith, and other artists.
Photographs are of Smith, family members, artwork, his studio, exhibition openings and other art events, and friends and colleagues. A family photograph dates from circa 1900 and negatives from 1920. Most of the photographs date from the 1940s through 1990s. Audio recordings include reel to reel tape of reviews of Smith's artwork by John Fitz Gibbon and nine cassettes of a lecture series organized by Smith at the San Francisco Art Institute.
Index Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following index terms.
Subjects-Topical:
Artists' studios -- Photographs; Art -- Study and teaching; Educators -- California -- Berkeley; Painters -- California; Women artists
Types of Materials:
Christmas cards; Interviews; Photographs; Sketches; Sound recordings; Writings
Names:
Anglim, Paule; Bischoff, Elmer, 1916-1991; Butterfield, Jan; Emmerich, André; Fitz Gibbon, John; Gimpel, Charles; Still, Clyfford,1904-; Still, Patricia; Swanson, Kathryn; Thiebaud, Wayne; Wollard, Robert; Gimpel Fils; New Arts (Art gallery)
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 8 series:
Series 1: Biographical Materials, 1930-2004 (Box 1; 0.25 linear feet)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1930s-2003 (Boxes 1-2; 1.0 linear foot)
Series 3: Personal Business Materials, 1953-2003 (Box 2; 0.25 linear feet)
Series 4: Teaching Materials, 1960s-1980s (Box 2; 18 folders)
Series 5: Writings, 1940s-1994 (Box 2; 0.25 linear feet)
Series 6: Artwork, 1928-1995 (Box 2; 8 folders)
Series 7: Printed Materials, 1928-2003 (Boxes 2-4; 1.25 linear feet)
Series 8: Photographs, 1900s-2001 (Box 4; 0.5 linear feet)
Series 9: Audio Recordings, 1965-1980 (Box 4; 6 items)
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Materials, 1930-1990, 2004, Series 1:; (Box 1; 0.25 linear feet)
  Biographical materials include biographical sketches, curriculum vitae, interview questions for an interview with Paul Karlstrom, a transcript of an in-depth interview with Jan Butterfield, and a questionnaire about Smith's career with responses. Also found are appointment books from 1974-1978, school ephemera, genealogical materials, loose notes, addresses, and miscellaneous papers related to organizations to which Smith belonged or was active.
  - Address Books, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Addresses, circa 1950s-1980s, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
  - Appointment Books, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Appointment Books, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Appointment Books, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Appointment Books, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Art Students League of San Francisco, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Autograph Book, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Biographical Sketches, 1960s-1987 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Boy Scout Cards, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Business Cards, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - College Materials, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Curriculum Vitae, 1964-1990s (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Drivers License, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Fundraiser, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Genealogical Materials, 1960s (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - High School Materials, 1931-1932 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Interview Questions for an Interview with Paul Karlstrom, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Transcript of Interview with Jan Butterfield, circa 1980s (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Maps, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Membership Cards, circa 1960s-1980s (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Notes, circa 1950s-1980s (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Oath of Allegiance, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Phone Messages, circa 1950s-1980s (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Publication List, 1960s (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Questionnaires, circa 1970s (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Reading List, circa 1979 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - San Francisco Art Institute, 1960s (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Tickets, 1970-early 1980s (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Who's Who Materials, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Correspondence, 1930s-2003, Series 2:; (Boxes 1-2; 1.0 linear foot)
  This series consists of Smith's correspondence with family, artists, former students, galleries, universities, and friends. Among the correspondents are artists Elmer Bischoff, Wayne Thiebaud, and Clyfford and Patricia Still, and art dealers Paule Anglim, Andre Emmerich, Charles Gimpel, and Kathryn Swanson of the New Arts Gallery. Family correspondence is from Smith's second wife, Donna, his sons Joseph and Bruce, and his stepsons Mark and Stephen. Additional letters are from friends, including Henri Lenoir, the founder of San Francisco bohemian cafe, and artist and writer Robert Wollard. Wollard letters are not only written as himself, but also as various characters associated with the "Natural Surrealist Party" and the Firesign Theatre. Also of interest are a letter to Thomas Albright in response to Albright's review of a Smith exhibition, and letters to Lawrence Ferlinghetti discussing the provenance of Smith's paintings in Ferlinghetti's possession. There is a group of illustrated letters sent to Smith upon the release of Hassel Smith: Drawings and Poems in 1999. These include letters from Frank Lobdell, Nathan Oliveira, and Wayne Thiebaud.
  Named files were established for those correspondents with more than scattered letters. The remaining correspondence is filed in general alphabetical files.
  - A, 1965-1997 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Albemarle Gallery, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Tom Albright, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - American Museum in Britain, 1972-1974 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Andre Emmerich Gallery, 1961-1997 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Archives of American Art, 1978-1986 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Robert Arneson, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - B-Bl, 1961-1994 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Bo-Bu, 1970-2000 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Tony Berlant, 1992-2001 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Elmer Bischoff, 1975-1989 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Bristol Polytechnic, 1972-1978 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Bill Brown, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - C-Ch, 1967-2002 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Ci-Cr, 1964-1994 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Madeline and Michael Canney, 1978-1992 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Christy [?], 1999 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - City and County of San Francisco, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - D, 1966-1983 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - David Stuart Galleries, 1965-1993 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Roy Deforest, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Mag Diamond, 1999, (illustrated letter by Charlie [?] on other side) (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Richard Diebenkorn, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - E, 1974-1983 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Charles Eckart, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - F, 1968-1998 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Family Correspondence, 1930s-1968 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Farewell Card, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - June Felter, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Lawrence Ferlinghetti, 1980-1987 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Ferus Gallery, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - G, 1969-1999 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Gallery Paule Anglim, 1976-1997, (9 folders) (Box 1, Folder 65-73)
  - Gimpel Fils, 1961-2003 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Glenna [?] and Charlie [?], 1999 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - H, 1972-2002 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Peter Hadiaris, 1991-1996 (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Mark Harrington, 1969-2000 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Stephen Harrington, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - I, 1974-1994 (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Iannetti Lazone Gallery, 1988-1990 (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - J, 1975-1992 (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - John Berggruen Gallery, 1981-1986 (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - John Natsoulas Gallery, 1992-2002 (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - K, 1976-1992 (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - Karl Kasten, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - L, 1966-2002 (Box 1, Folder 87)
  - Susan Landauer, 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 88)
  - Henri Lenoir, 1974-1991 (Box 1, Folder 89)
  - Frank Lobdell, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 90)
  - M, 1959-2000 (Box 1, Folder 91)
  - Magnolia Editions, 1986-2002 (Box 1, Folder 92)
  - Peter and Madeline Martin, 1975-1989 (Box 1, Folder 93)
  - Robert and Mary McChesney, 1968-1985 (Box 1, Folder 94)
  - N, 1968-1997 (Box 1, Folder 95)
  - Natsoulas Novelozo Gallery, 1989-1994 (Box 1, Folder 96)
  - Manuel Neri, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 97)
  - Northwestern University, 1934-1996 (Box 1, Folder 98)
  - O, 1978-1983 (Box 1, Folder 99)
  - Oakland Museum, 1965-1985 (Box 1, Folder 100)
  - Nathan Oliveira, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 101)
  - P, 1972-2003 (Box 1, Folder 102)
  - Ralph Petty, 1976-1991 (Box 1, Folder 103)
  - Kevin Power, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 104)
  - R, 1964-1990 (Box 1, Folder 105)
  - Deborah Remington, 1977-1993 (Box 1, Folder 106)
  - S-Sh, 1965-1997 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Si-Su, 1969-2002 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Salander-O'Reilly Gallery, 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - San Francisco Museum of Modern Art, 1974-1996 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - San Francisco Art Institute, 1982-1995 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - San Jose Museum of Art, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Barbara Scales, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Peter Selz, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Bruce Smith, 1973-1995 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Donna Smith, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Joe Smith, circa 1970s-1990s (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Terry St. John, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Clyfford Still, 1966-1979 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Pat Still, 1965-1994 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Kathryn Swanson, 1960-1986 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - T, 1972-2000 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Allan Temko, 1972-1981 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Wayne Thiebaud, 1967-1976 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Thomas McLintock and Co., 1972-1979, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 19-20)
  - U, 1966-2002 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - University of California, Berkeley, 1977-1992 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - University of California, Berkeley, 1965-1989 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - V, 1977-1983 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - W, 1968-1991 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Muriel Watson, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Robert Wollard, 1970s-2000, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 27-28)
  - Worcester Art Museum, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - C.W. Younger, 1967-1969 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Z, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Unknown Correspondents, 1958-1984 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Personal Business Records, 1953-2003, Series 3:; (Box 2; 0.25 linear feet)
  Personal business records document Smith's finances, exhibitions, and his business with galleries and museums. There are also records related to his personal finances. Found are consignment forms, records of gifts, price lists, exhibition checklists, guest lists, loan records, shipping records, condition reports, conservation reports, and court records from a case against the Iannetti/Lanzone Gallery.
  - Agreements, 1978-1993 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Art Materials, 1964-1977 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Condition Report, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Conservation Reports, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Consignment Forms, 1984-1990 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Court Materials, 1970-1996, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 38-39)
  - Customs Declaration, circa 1979-1990 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Exhibition Checklists, 1961-1988, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 41-42)
  - Expense Books, 1961-1965 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Expenses, 1960s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Financial Materials, 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Gallery Floor Plans, circa 1980s (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Gifts, 1966-2003 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Grant Applications, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Guest Lists, 1960s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - House Sales, 1962-1966 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Inventories, 1988-1992 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - King Ubu Gallery Exhibitions, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Loans, 1988-2002 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Medical Expenses, 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Notes, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Oakland Museum Holdings, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Object Records, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Permissions, 1990-1994 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Price Lists, 1987-1998 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Print Documentation, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Sales, 1965-1989 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Shipping Records, 1966-1977 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Shipping Records, 1977-1995 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Taxes, 1961-1990, (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 64-67)
- Teaching Materials, 1960s-1980s, Series 4:; (Box 2; 17 folders)
  Teaching materials includes Smith's notes on art and art history, student handouts, syllabi, employment information, and administrative documents. There are surprisingly few records in this series, given the extent of Smith's teaching career and lectures. There do not appear to be any records in his papers documenting his teaching career in England.
  - American Art and Literature, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Artistic Forms, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Artistic Traits, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Book Excepts, 1970s (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Bristol Polytechnic, 1970-1977, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 72-73)
  - Class Schedule, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - Employment Certification (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - Illusion, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1966-1974 (Box 2, Folder 77)
  - Notes, circa 1960s-circa 1970s (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - Posters, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 79)
  - Projects, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 80)
  - Seminar Schedules, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 81)
  - Student Lists, 1978-1980 (Box 2, Folder 82)
  - Subject/Object, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 83)
  - Syllabi, 1968-1970 (Box 2, Folder 84)
  - Notes on Women Artists, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 85)
- Writings, 1940s-1994, Series 5:; (Box 2; 0.25 linear feet)
  Writings and fragments by Smith concern the art market, art institutions, and social criticism. Of special interest is a lengthy essay by Smith about the art community in San Francisco.
  Writings by others include essays about Smith and his work, and quotations and essays by artists and critics. Also found are writings by friends Henri Lenoir and Robert Wollard, an entry from the journal of his son Joseph, and essays about art and literature in San Francisco.
  - [Al and Phyllis], circa 1960s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 86)
  - Alphabet For Adults, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 87)
  - Aphorisms, circa 1940s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 88)
  - The Appeal to Reason, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 89)
  - Art in Action, circa 1952 (Box 2, Folder 90)
  - Artist Statements, circa 1960s-1980s (Box 2, Folder 91)
  - Art and Information Theory, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 92)
  - Fragments, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 93)
  - Letters of Recommendation, 1977-1980 (Box 2, Folder 94)
  - Los Angeles County Museum of Art, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 95)
  - [The Middle Class], 1979 (Box 2, Folder 96)
  - The Nettlecomb Exhibition, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 97)
  - [On Art Criticism and Galleries], circa 1960s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 98)
  - [On Article By Patrick Heron], circa 1970s (Box 2, Folder 99)
  - [On Painting], 1977 (Box 2, Folder 100)
  - [On the Los Angeles County Museum of Art], 1977 (Box 2, Folder 101)
  - On the San Francisco School of Painting, circa 1956 (Box 2, Folder 102)
  - [On Uncle Tom's Cabin], 1992 (Box 2, Folder 103)
  - Poems, circa 1940s-1980s (Box 2, Folder 104)
  - Recent Pronouncements, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 105)
  - [Restraint/Chance/Pattern], circa 1950s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 106)
  - [Sebastapolecats], 1950s (Box 2, Folder 107)
  - [Statements and Quotations By Hassel Smith and Others], 1970s-1980s (Box 2, Folder 108)
  - Writings by Others (Box 2)
    - "Lily Fenichel" by Robert Duncan, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 109)
    - [Poems by Ralph Waldo Emerson], circa 1960s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 110)
    - "Hassel Smith's Resistance" by Chelsea Gilmore, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 111)
    - [From The Literary World of San Francisco and Its Environs by Don Herron], 1985 (Box 2, Folder 112)
    - "Cookie, You're Number One" by Henri Lenoir, circa 1980-1986 (Box 2, Folder 113)
    - "Letter to the Editor" by Henri Lenoir, 1980s (Box 2, Folder 114)
    - "Hassel Smith" by Douglas Macagy, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 115)
    - "American Artists Exhibition" by Maggie Mash, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 116)
    - "Hassel Smith" by Bruce Nixon, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 117)
    - "How Black Was the Cat" by Anne Frisbie O'Neill, circa 1950s-1980s (Box 2, Folder 118)
    - [Picasso Quotations], circa 1960s-1980s (Box 2, Folder 119)
    - "A Conversation With Hassel Smith" by Kevin Power, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 2, Folder 120)
    - "Myths and Rituals of the Avant Garde" by Harold Rosenberg, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 121)
    - "Movement For Rethinking Art and Design Education" by Pilar Saizar, circa 1970s (Box 2, Folder 122)
    - [Journal Entry] by Joseph Smith, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 123)
    - [Leo Stein quote], 1947 (Box 2, Folder 124)
    - "Hassel Smith" by Allan Temko, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 125)
    - [Possible Transcript of an Interview], 1961 (Box 2, Folder 126)
    - "Su-dra the Lion" by [unknown], circa 1940s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 127)
    - [Writings by Robert Wollard], circa 1960s-1980s (Box 2, Folder 128)
- Artwork, 1928-1995, Series 6:; (Box 2; 8 folders)
  Scattered artwork by Smith includes handmade family Christmas cards, doodles and sketches, a folded paper fortune teller, and an exhibition announcement with humorous pen additions. Also found is artwork by others including Elmer Bischoff and Robert Wollard.
  - Altered Postcard, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 129)
    (exhibition announcement for Hassel Smith/Charles Strong with pen additions)